A Guide to the Bushrod Washington Family Papers, 1662-1835
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
Bushrod Washington Family Papers 1662-1835
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 2005.4
Regular and Oversize Items.
Papers of Bushrod Washington (1762-1829) and his family of Westmoreland County, Virginia; Washington, D.C.; and Jefferson County, VA (now West Virginia); consisting of letters, deeds, wills, other estate documents, surveys, and biographical information pertaining to three generations of the family
Bushrod Washington Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
On Deposit
Biographical Information
Bushrod Washington (1762-1829), was the son of John Augustine and Hannah (Bushrod) Washington. John Augustine Washington was the brother of President George Washington. Upon the death of the President, Bushrod Washington inherited the Mount Vernon estate. A graduate of the College of William and Mary, Bushrod Washington would serve as an associate justice of the U.S. Supreme Court. He was joined on the Supreme Court by his long-time friend, John Marshall. Justices Washington and Marshall had met while attending law lectures given by George Wythe at the College of William and Mary.
Judge Washington and his wife, Julia Ann Blackburn, had no children of their own, but raised three of their nephews. One nephew, John Augustine Washington, would inherit Mount Vernon from the Judge.
Scope and Content
The Bushrod Washington Family Papers consist of documents gathered by the descendents of the first President of the United States, George Washington. The collection comprises an assortment of correspondence and legal documents, documenting the lives and property ownership of several branches of the Washington family. The collection is organized into five series: Correspondence, Legal Documents, Social, Miscellaneous, and Indenture Notices (Land Deeds).
The Correspondence series, circa 1780 - circa 1835 (.3 linear feet), contains letters mostly written to Bushrod Washington, nephew of the General (as the family referred to the first President), executor of the General's estate, and inheritor of Mount Vernon. While some were written by friends of Bushrod Washington, most are from his brother, and his many nieces and nephews. Of the letters not written to Bushrod Washington, the largest portion were written by Bushrod C. Washington, his wife, Anna Maria, and their daughter Hannah to their son Cadet Thomas Washington. Cadet Washington was stationed in Middletown, CT. Most often, when one of the three would pen a letter, the other two would add a quick greeting in whatever space remained. Among the famous Virginians with whom Bushrod Washington corresponded are Richard Channing Moore, George Spotswood, and George Wythe. All of the letters are in alphabetical order by the last name of the correspondent.
Legal Documents, 1719-1830 (.3 linear feet), contains several subseries: Estate Matters, Financial agreements, Land Disputes, Plats, Wills, and Other. Issues arising after the death of a family member can be found in the Estate Matters subseries. The estate of Genl. George Washington was perhaps the most disputed, with legal proceedings occurring thirty years following his death. Loans and sales of property are the focus of the Financial Agreements subseries. At least two family members were involved with land disputes over the years. The Land Disputes subseries records the disputes of Richard Bushrod and John Augustine Washington. Surveys, or Plats, of the land were a primary tool for settling such disputes and can be found in the next subseries. The Wills of several family members provide data regarding the families' possessions. This subseries contains wills written by ten family members. In addition to household items and distribution of land, these mainly eighteenth century wills also dictate the owners' desires regarding who would inherit the slaves. Four other documents, not closely resembling any of the other legal pieces comprise their own subseries. When possible, all of the Legal Documents are listed in alphabetical order by the last name of the creator.
Bushrod Washington, a well respected Judge, was active in affairs aside from running his family estate. Evidence of some of these can be found in the Social series, 1816-1829 (.1 linear feet). The American Bible Society and the Bunker Hill Monument Association were among the organizations in which Judge Washington was involved. The organizations are listed alphabetically.
A formula for cement, mailed to the President of the United States, Mount Vernon, and muffin recipes highlight the Miscellaneous series, 1795 and undated (.1 linear feet).
Some of the oldest material in the collection is found in the Indenture Notices (Land Deeds) series, 1662-1798 (.3 linear feet). These documents relate the history of land ownership among the Bushrod and Washington families, as well as several of their neighbors and associates. While technically legal documents, the size of several of the deeds precludes their being stored alongside the papers of the Legal Documents series. Arranged alphabetically by the grantor of the land, the Indenture Notices specify all the details of the transaction, including the amount of land, location, and purchase price.
Arrangement
The contents are arranged by topic and chronologically.
Index Terms
Persons:
Washington, Bushrod, 1762-1829; Wythe, George; Washington, Bushrod C.; Washington, Anna Maria.; Washington, Hannah; Moore, Richard Channing, 1762-1841; Spotswood, George
Family Names:
Washington family
Corporate Names:
American Bible Society
Subjects:
Wills; Slavery; Deeds; Administration of estates; Maps; Indentures
Geographical Names:
Mount Vernon (Va.: Estate)
Collection Contents
- Correspondence
  - Babier, Urbain, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bladget, Rebecca, December 1, 1829 (Folder 2)
  - Caldwell, Charles, May 13, 1814. (Folder 3)
  - Duvall, Gabreil, August 31, 1829. (Folder 4)
  - Garvard, William, March 18, 1825. (Folder 5)
  - Hamilton, Elizabeth (Mrs. Alexander) and Washington, Bushrod, Ca. 1818-Ca.1825. (Folder 6)
  - Lee, Edmund Jennings, January 31, 1828. (Folder 7)
  - Mason, John, April 24, 1829. (Folder 8)
  - Moore, Richard Channing, December 17, 1813. (Folder 9)
  - Peters, Richard, 1826 1828. (Folder 10)
  - Preto, Mary, March 23, 1829. (Folder 11)
  - Scott, Elizabeth Blackburn, 1816-1826 (scattered) (Folder 12)
  - Scott, G. H., July 29, 1825. (Folder 13)
  - Sparks, Jared, 1827 1835. (Folder 14)
  - Spotswood, George, March8, 1829. (Folder 15)
  - Stockton, Richard, July 12, 1827. (Folder 16)
  - Story, Joseph, 1816 1821. (Folder 17)
  - Washington, Anna Maria, August 23, 1829. (Folder 18)
  - Washington, Bushrod, Miscellaneous outgoing correspondence (copies), Ca. 1817-Ca. 1818. (Folder 19)
  - Washington, Bushrod C., 1823-1827 (scattered) (Folder 20)
  - Washington, Bushrod, Jr. (Folder 21)
  - Washington, Bushrod C. et al, 1828-1832, (5 folders) (Folder 22-26)
  - Washington, Corbin, Ca. 1780s-Ca. 1790s, (2 folders) (Folder 27-28)
  - Washington, George Augustine, June 24, 1782. (Folder 29)
  - Washington, Hannah, 1782-1798. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Washington, Jane Charlotte, 1827 1828 (Folder 2)
  - Washington, John Augustine, Ca. 1782-Ca. 1784, (2 folders) (Folder 3-4)
  - Washington, Lund, undated. (Folder 5)
  - Washington, Samuel George, June 20, 1824. (Folder 6)
  - Wythe, George, 1785 1787. (Folder 7)
- Legal documents
  - Estate Matters
    - Inventory, Estate of John Augustine Washington, Ca 1785 (Folder 8)
    - Land left to Samuel and John Augustine Washington, Ca. 1750 (Folder 9)
    - Washington, Genl. George
      - Correspondence, Ca. 1818-Ca. 1829 (Folder 10)
      - Court documents, November 1826 (Folder 11)
      - Financial transactions, Ca. 1803-Ca. 1824 (Folder 12)
      - Land plat, Jefferson County, Ca. July 1805 (Folder 13)
    - Washington, Bushrod (Folder 14)
  - Financial Agreements
    - Champe, William and Servis Willis (witnessed by Charles Washington), June 19, 1778 (Folder 15)
    - Washington, Bushrod and Henry Lee, 1795 1798 (Folder 16)
    - Washington, Corbin and David Smedley, February 11, 1796 (Folder 17)
    - Washington, Corbin and Bushrod Washington, January 8, 1797. (Folder 18)
    - Washington, John and Robert Throckmorton, undated (Folder 19)
  - Land Disputes
    - Bushrod, Richard and McNemarra, Lawrence, 1736 (Folder 20)
    - Nichols, John and Webb, William, undated (Folder 21)
    - Washington, John Augustine, Ca. 1773 (Folder 22)
  - Plats
    - Bath (Present day Berkeley Springs, WV), undated (Folder 23)
    - Land of Bushrod C. Washington, et al, undated (Folder 24)
    - Land of Corbin Washington, 1789 1793 (Folder 25)
    - Land of John Augustine Washington, Ca. 1815 (Folder 26)
    - Land of Robert Worthington, April 24, 1734 and undated (Folder 27)
  - Wills
    - Bushrod, John, 1719 (Folder 28)
    - Bushrod, John, 1760 (Folder 29)
    - Bushrod, Thomas, 1697 (Folder 30)
    - Johnston, Robert, 1765 (Folder 31)
    - Lee, Richard, 1790 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Washington, Bushrod, February 12, 1830 (Folder 2)
    - Washington, George Steptoe, 1807 (Folder 3)
    - Washington, Hannah, undated (Folder 4)
    - Washington, John Augustine, 1784 1785 (Folder 5)
    - Washington, John A., 1830 (Folder 6)
  - Other
    - Appointment of deputies to John Bushrod, June 26, 1759 (Folder 7)
    - Insurance Policy, Home of Bushrod Washington, 1796 (Folder 8)
    - Petition, rough draft, undated (Folder 9)
    - Property sold at Selby and Valuation of Negroes, January 12, 1813 (Folder 10)
- Social
  - American Bible Society, 1816-1825 (Folder 11)
  - American Sunday School Union, 1829 (Folder 12)
  - Bunker Hill Monument Association, 1825 (Folder 13)
  - Philadelphia Southern Society, 1818 (Folder 14)
  - Solicitation for money, 1828 (Folder 15)
  - University honors, 1824-1829 (Folder 16)
- Miscellaneous
  - Appointment of Commissioners, Maryland, December 21, 1795 (Folder 17)
  - Formula for cement, undated (Folder 18)
  - Recipes, undated (Folder 19)
- Indenture Notices (Land Deeds)
  - Brittain, Samuel to James [Taffy], October 15, 1711 (Box 4 (Oversize))
  - Bryant, Daniel and Frances to John Bushrod, October 3, 1716 (2 copies)
  - Bushrod, Thomas to John Bushrod November 27, 1682
  - Culpeper, Marguritte Lady and Catherine Lady Fairfax to John Bushrod, September 24, 1710
  - Fredericksburg, Trustees of to John Waller
  - Griffith, David to James McCracken, April 5, 1750.
  - Lee, Charles and Ann to Corbin Washington, October 15, 1798.
  - Little, Archibald (Estate of) to Thomas Bushrod, March 7, 1695 (2 pieces)
  - Maddocks, Rice to Richard Bushrod, November 29, 1662
  - Soarles, George to John Bushrod, March 22, 1693
  - Waller, John to Augustine Washington, March 3, 1741
  - Washington, Richard Henry Lee to John A. Washington and Bushrod Corbin Washington, January 17, 1814.
  - Washington, John Augustine to Mary Washington, May 22, 1778
  - Worthington, Jr., Robert and Margaret to Robert Worthington, III, March 29, 1768
  - Worthington, Robert to John Augustine Washington, April 1, 1768.